Inventory of the V. N. Zhernakov Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
V. N. Zhernakov Papers
1862-1976
2002C68
Zhernakov, V. N. (Vladimir Nikolaevich), 1909-1977.
35 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes 14.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, printed matter, and photographs of Zhernakov, a russian émigré scholar in Manchuria, Australia and the United States. Materials relate to the society, culture and natural history of Manchuria, and to Russian émigré affairs.
Administrative Information
Access
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2002.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1909 August 21 Born, Omsk, Siberia
1921 Arrived in Harbin and enrolled for study at the Commercial High School
1926 Entered the Harbin Juridical Institute
1946 Appointed assistant dean of the Economic-Engineering Department of the Harbin Polytechnic Institute, where he also taught and directed the Research Sector
1951-1959 Deputy director of the Obshchestvo Izucheniia Man’chzhurskogo, Kraia, Harbin
1959-1962 Research consultant at the Obshchestvo Izucheniia Man’chzhurskogo, Kraia, Harbin
1962 Left Harbin for Australia
1963-1971 Director of the YMCA in Yallourn
1972 Emigrated to the United States
1977 February 15 Died, Oakland, California
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of Vladimir Zhernakov, acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2002, relate mainly to culture, society and natural history in Manchuria during the first half of the 20th century. Vladimir Zhernakov continued his career as a scholar of Far Eastern natural history after his departure from Harbin, Manchuria, in 1962.
The bulk of the collection consists of Zhernakov's writings, which describe the area of Harbin and include topics of natural history in Manchuria. Zhernakov also wrote several biographies of prominent Russian émigré scientists. Also included are important writings on Russian émigré activities in Harbin.
Of significance is the published material, which includes rare Russian émigré newspapers and serials. Printed matter and other publications relate primarily to the study of natural history and to various aspects of Harbin, Manchuria.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Manchuria (China); Russians--China.; Russians--Australia.; Russians--United States.
Container List
- Surin, V. I. (Box 1)
  - Lesnoe delo v Man'chzhurii, Ekonomicheskoe Biuro Kitaiskoi Vostochnoi Zheleznoi Dorogi, Kharhin, 1930 (Box 1)
  - Promyshlennost' Severnoi Man'chzhurii i Kharbina, Ekonomicheskoe Biuro Kitaiskoi Vostochnoi Zheleznoi Dorogi, Kharbin, 1928 (Box 1)
- China Journal (Shanghai), 1934 November (Box 1)
  Vol. XXI, No. 5
- Lobanoff, M. M., "Paintings and Sketches of Manchuria and Korea,", 1971 (Box 1)
- Pamphlets authored by Vladimir Zhernakov, 1968-1975. (Box 1)
  In Russian and English
- Zapiski Kharbinskogo Obshchestva Estestvoispytatelei i Etnografov, No. 1, Etnografiia, Kharbinskoe Obshchestvo Estestvoispytatelei I Etnografov, Kharbin, 1946 (Box 1)
- Published book, in Japanese, entitled Manchurian Situation, 1939. (Box 1)
  Consists of photographs depicting scenes in Manchuria
- Maksimovich, K. I., Amurskii krai, Imperatorskaia Akademiia Nauk, 1862 (Box 2)
- Sbornik Gosudarstvennogo Pedagogicheskogo Instituta, gorod Kharbin, 1925-1937 (Box 2)
- Books and pamphlets by Vladimir Zhernakov and other authors relating to agriculture, forestry, natural history and descriptions of the Siberian Far East and Manchuria, 1909-1962. (Box 2)
  In Russian
- Photographs depicting flowers, plants, exhibitions of natural science, and various individuals in Harbin, 1936-1944 (Box 3)
- Pamphlets relating to biology, botany and marine life in Manchuria and Japan by various Japanese authors, 1973 (Box 3)
- Writings by Vladimir Zhernakov relating to Manchuria and Mongolia, 1976. (Box 3)
  Includes correspondence and photographs depicting Mongolia and Tibet, undated
- Writings by Vladimir Zhernakov and others relating to natural history and other aspects of China and Manchuria, 1975. (Box 3)
  Includes photographs depicting Manchuria and the Holy Land, undated
- Clippings from the Russian émigré press of articles by Vladimir Zhernakov and others relating to various aspects of China and the Russian émigré community, 1928-1967 (Box 3)
- Rubezh (Harbin), 1929-1941 (Box 3)
- Compilation of Russian language publications in Australia, 1929-1975. (Box 4)
- Writings by Vladimir Zhernakov and others relating to various aspects of Manchuria, 1920-1970. (Box 4)
- Writings by Vladimir Zhernakov on various subjects, 1930-1973. (Box 4)
  In English and Russian. Includes correspondence in English
- Clippings from the Russian émigré press, 1932-1977 (Box 4)
- Correspondence, 1961-1972 (Box 5)
- Photographs of Russian Orthodox clergy, circa 1930-1940 (Box 5)
- Printed matter relating to Manchuria and Harbin, 1930-1974. (Box 5)
  Includes clippings from the Russian émigré press
- Writings by V. Zhernakov, primarily in Russian (Box 5)
  - General, 1930-1945 (Box 5)
  - Relating to T. P. Gordeiev and I. G. Baranov, 1966-1971 (Box 5)
- Harbin, brochures relating to the city, 1930-1945 (Box 5)
- Writings by V. Zhernakov and others relating to Harbin, 1930-1972. (Box 6)
  Primarily in Russian
- Clippings from the Russian émigré press, 1955-1975 (Box 6)
- Writings by Vladimir Zhernakov and others. Primarily in Russian (Box 6)
  - Sugar industry in southeast China, 1939-1957 (Box 6)
  - Wildlife in northeast China, 1971 (Box 6)
- Den' politekhnika (Kharbin), 1930 January (Box 6)
- Biographical material, including bibliographies, relating to V. Zhernakov, 1945-1976 (Box 7)
- Clippings from the Russian émigré press, 1969-1973 (Box 7)
- Writings and notes by V. Zhernakov, 1966-1975. (Box 7)
- Writings by Vladimir Zhernakov and other materials relating to Mikhail Lobanov, 1964 (Box 7)
- Anent, Eduard. Biographical material, 1940-1973. (Box 8)
  Includes correspondence, clippings and writings by V. Zhernakov
- Baikov, Nikolai. Biographical material, 1935-1967. (Box 8)
- Drawings with Chinese characters, circa 1930s (Box 8)
- Ponosov, Vladimir V. Writings by V. Zhernakov, undated. (Box 8)
  In English
- Printed matter relating to Australia, 1967-1969 (Box 8)
- Alin, Vasilii N. Biographical material, 1966 (Box 9)
- Australian atlas, undated (Box 9)
- Australian calendars, 1974-1976 (Box 9)
- Baikov, Nikolai. Writings, 1925. (Box 9)
- Kozlov, Innokentii V. Biographical material, 1926-1964. (Box 9)
  Includes correspondence
- Russian émigré press in Australia, 1965-1973. (Box 9)
  Printed matter Speech by V. Zhernakov relating to the Harbin Museum, undated Tasmania. Clippings and printed matter, 1963-1971
- Writings by Vladimir Zhernakov (Box 9)
  - Aleksandrov, Aleksandr I., undated (Box 9)
  - Kharbinskii Politekhnicheskii Institut, 1968 (Box 9)
  - McMillan, Angus, undated (Box 9)
  - Rerikh, N. K., undated (Box 9)
  - Shkurkin, Pavel V., 1972. (Box 9)
- Writings by Vladimir Zhernakov and others relating to China, Manchuria, and Harbin, 1937-1964 (Box 9)
- Baikov, Nikolai, V debriakh Man'chzhurii, Kharbin, 1934 (Box 10)
- Correspondence, 1965-1972 (Box 10)
- Naturalist Man'chzhurii (Kharbin), 1936-1937 (Box 10)
- Printed matter and published material (Box 10)
  - Australia, 1967-1973 (Box 10)
  - Chinese language, 1958 (Box 10)
  - Russian language, 1931-1956 (Box 10)
- Writings by Vladimir Zhernakov and others on a variety of subjects, 1935-1978 (Box 10)
- Books, pamphlets, and printed matter relating to agriculture, geography, natural history, and other subjects in Manchuria and the Far East, 1931-1965. (Box 11)
  Includes writings by Vladimir Zhernakov
- Izvestiia Kluba Estestvoznaniia I Geografii KhSML (Harbin), 1941 (Box 12)
- Izvestiia Obshchestva Izucheniia Man'chzhurskogo Kraia (Harbin), 1928 (Box 12)
  No. 7
- Pamphlets and printed matter relating to various aspects of China and Manchuria, 1939-1970. (Box 12)
  Includes writings by V. Zhernakov
- Trudy Sungariiskoi rechnoi biologicheskoi stantsii (Harbin), 1925-1928 (Box 12)
- Uchenyi zapiski istoriko-filologicheskogo fakul'teta v g. Vladivostoke (Vladivostok), 1919 (Box 12)
- Zapiski Kharbinskogo Obshchestva Estestoispytatelei i Etnografov (Harbin), 1946-1950 (Box 12)
- Correspondence, 1962-1974 (Box 13)
- Diploma and report cards of Vladimir and Maria Zhernakov, 1920 (Box 13)
- Izvestiia Kluba Estestvoznaiia i Geografii KhSML (Harbin), 1945 (Box 13)
- "Kitaiskaia muzyka," Vestnik Azii, 1924 (Box 13)
  No. 51
- Ocherki stran Dal'nego Vostoka (Harbin), 1931 (Box 13)
- Pamphlets and printed matter relating to botany and natural history in Australia and China, 1920-1970 (Box 13)
- Correspondence (Box 14)
  - 1962-1976 (Box 14)
  - 1935-1976 (Box 15)
- Chinese language book, entitled International Chess Positions, Shanghai, 1961 (Box 16)
- Correspondence, 1936-1976 (Box 16)
- The Silver Elephant, Collier-Macmillan, 1964 (Box 16)
- Correspondence, 1962-1974 (Box 17)
- Lessons in Lettering, McGraw-Hill Book Company, 1921 (Box 17)
- Map of the Tsitsikar area in Manchuria, 1902 (Box 17)
- Writings by Vladimir Zhernakov (Box 18)
  - Gapanovich, Ivan I., 1974. (Box 18)
    Includes biographical materials
  - Harbin, Manchuria, and northeast China, 1962-1974. (Box 18)
    Includes clippings and correspondence
  - Kormazov, Vladimir A., 1974. (Box 18)
- Writings by Vladimir Zhernakov (Box 19)
  - Australia and China, 1966-1969 (Box 19)
  - Avtonomov, Nikolai P., 1971 (Box 19)
  - Clippings relating to various Russian émigré subjects, 1967-1974 (Box 19)
  - Gordeev, Taras P., undated (Box 19)
  - Lake Tyers, undated (Box 19)
  - Miklukho-Maklai, Nikolai N., 1948-1969. (Box 19)
    Includes writings by others
  - Soils and plants of Long Island at Lakes Entrance, 1963 (Box 19)
- Biographical material, 1944-1964 (Box 20)
- Correspondence, 1963-1984 (Box 20)
- Topkapi Museum, Bellci Ofset, Ankara, undated (Box 20)
- Zheleznodorzhnik (Harbin), 1941 (Box 20)
  No. 55
- Correspondence, 1962-1976 (Box 21)
- Photographs of Vladimir and Maria Zhernakov and others, 1919-1967 (Box 21)
- Biographical material, 1905-1971 (Box 22)
- Correspondence, 1921-1976 (Box 22)
- Pamphlets, in Chinese, 1956 (Box 22)
- Photographs of Vladimir and Maria Zhernakov and others, undated (Box 22)
- Biographical material, undated (Box 23)
- Correspondence, 1963-1976 (Box 23)
- Photographs of Vladimir and Maria Zhernakov and others, 1924-1972 (Box 23)
- Photographs, postcards, and 35mm slides of Vladimir and Maria Zhernakov, other individuals, and scenes in various parts of the world, 1940-1970 (Box 24)
- Photographs and postcards of Vladimir and Maria Zhernakov, other individuals, and scenes in various parts of the world, 1928-1970 (Box 25-27)
- Pamphlets relating to geography and natural history in Australia and the Russian Orthodox Church abroad, 1960-1975 (Box 28)
- Photographs and 35mm slides of Vladimir and Maria Zhernakov, other individuals, and scenes in various parts of the world, 1972-1975 (Box 28)
- Clippings from the Russian émigré press relating to Harbin, Manchuria and the Far East, 1930-1972 (Box 29)
- Manchuria-Graph, 1937 (Box 29)
  Vol. V, No. 9
- Nikitin, Mstislav and Sofiia, writings, 1966-1968 (Box 29)
- Photographs of scenes in Manchuria and Australia, 1928-1970 (Box 29)
- Writings by Vladimir Zhernakov. Primarily in Russian (Box 29)
  - General, 1972-1973 (Box 29)
  - Gordeev, Taras Petrovich, 1960-1967 (Box 29)
- Adamov, A., G. I. Shelikhov, Izdatel'stvo Pravda, Moscow, 1951 (Box 30)
- Australia, various printed matter relating to, 1928-1971 (Box 30)
- Baranov, I. G., writings, 1938 (Box 30)
- Drawings by Vladimir Zhernakov, 1925-1937 (Box 30)
- Izvestiia i trudy Kharbinskogo Politekhnicheskogo Instituta (Harbin), 1931-1932 (Box 30)
  Tom piatyi
- Japan, Nelson Doubleday, Inc., 1966 (Box 30)
- Obshchestvo Izucheniia Man'chzhurskogo Kraia, Otchet, undated (Box 30)
- Writings by Vladimir Zhernakov, 1934-1974. (Box 30)
- Zapiski Kharbinskogo Obshchestva Estestvoispytatelei i Etnografov (Harbin), 1954 (Box 30)
  No. 11
- Australia, clippings and printed matter relating to, 1943-1965 (Box 31)
- Clippings, publications and printed matter from the Russian émigré press, relating primarily to Harbin and Manchuria, 1929-1945 (Box 31)
- Diary, 1937 (Box 31)
- Photographs of landscape, waterways, and geological formations, undated (Box 31)
- Writings by Vladimir Zhernakov (Box 31)
  - Beekeeping and botany in Australia, 1968. (Box 31)
    Includes notes, clippings, and photographs
  - Gins, Georgii, 1971 (Box 31)
  - Sinology in Australia, 1966 (Box 31)
- Australia, publications and printed matter relating to, 1963-1967 (Box 32)
- Drawings by Vladimir Zhernakov, 1935-1937 (Box 32)
- Nikiforov, N. V., "Tserkovnaia arkheologiia v sviazi s istoriei iskusstv,", 1956 (Box 32)
- Photographs of Vladimir Zhernakov and other individuals in Harbin, Manchuria, circa 1940-1960 (Box 32)
- Australia, printed matter relating to geography and national parks, 1959-1965 (Box 33)
- Komissiia po izdaniiu Istoricheskogo Iubileinogo Obzora Kitaiskoi Vostochnoi zheleznoi dorogi, Kharbin, 1922 (Box 33)
  No. 44
- Maps of various parts of the world (Box 33)
  - General, circa 1940-1970 (Box 33)
  - German language maps, 1963-1965 (Box 33)
- Photographs of Vladimir Zhernakov, other individuals, and scenes in Manchuria, circa 1910-1950 (Box 33)
- Table of Chinese characters with Russian translations, undated (Box 33)
- Writings by Vladimir Zhernakov (Box 33)
  - Clippings relating to Harbin and Manchuria, 1930-1945 (Box 33)
  - "Pushnoe delo v Severnoi Man'chzhurii," Harbin, 1937 (Box 33)
- Correspondence, 1973-1977 (Box 34)
- Kitaiskaia Vostochnaia zheleznaia doroga, Severnaia Man'chzhuriia, Harbin, Tom I, 1916 (Box 34)
- Map of the Soviet Union depicting locations of various nationalities, 1951 (Box 34)
- "Our Herald" ("Nash vestnik"), newsletter of the trip of Russian immigrants to the United States from the Philippines aboard the USNS General W. G. Haan, 1951 January (Box 34)
- Printed matter relating to various subjects (Box 34)
  - English and Russian language, 1925-1970 (Box 34)
  - German language, 1938-1972 (Box 34)
- Writings by various authors and colleagues of Vladimir Zhernakov, 1928-1940 (Box 34)
- Writings by Vladimir Zhernakov, 1933-1975 (Box 34)
- Baranov, I. G., writings, 1926-1927 (Box 35)
- Kitaiskaia Vostochnaia zheleznaia doroga, Severnaia Man'chzhuriia, Harbin, Tom II, 1918 (Box 35)
- Obshchestvo Izucheniia Man'chzhurskogo Kraia, Harbin, publications, 1923-1929 (Box 35)
- Printed matter and publications relating to various aspects of Harbin, China, and Manchuria, 1915-1974 (Box 35)
- Tolmachev, V. Ia., writings, 1925-1932 (Box 35)
- Drawings, undated (Box 36)
- Kharbinskii vestnik (Harbin), clippings and separate issues, 1917-1926 (Box 36)
- Paintings, undated (Box 36)
- Photographs of Vladimir Zhernakov, other individuals, and scenes in Harbin, 1926-1935 (Box 36)
- Australia, printed matter and publications, circa 1964-1970 (Box 37)
- Biographical materials, 1937 (Box 37)
- Latrobe Valley Field Naturalists Club, newsletters and printed matter, 1964 (Box 37)
- Photographs (Box 37)
  - Harbin and other areas of Manchuria, undated (Box 37)
  - Unidentified individuals, undated (Box 37)
- Podobedova, Aleksandra (Box 37)
  - Biographical materials, 1916-1944 (Box 37)
  - Correspondence, 1941-1977 (Box 37)
- Rubezh (Harbin), 1929 (Box 37)
  No. 50